Administ rative relations
The administrative relations between the Union and the States offer yet another proof of the highly integrated
"nature of the Indian feder ation. Under the constitution the Union government can exercise the execut ive power in respect of all matters within its legislative j urisdiction. Some of these matters, such as customs, and central excise, income tax, Railways, post and Telegraphs are administer ed directly by services maintained by the Union Government. In most of the cases, the administration of Urnion matters is delegated to State authorities. In this respect, there is a striking contrast between the American and the Indian f ederal system. In the United States, the"
administrative systems o f the Union and the States run parallel. In India they meet at many points.
The Union-State administrative relations in India are organized as to enable the Union Government exercise
considerable direction and control over the administrative machiner y of the States. The constitut ion on places upon the States the obligation to exercise their executive authority in such a way as to ensure compliance with the Union
