A n assessment ot Centre-State Relations
"A critical examination of the legislative, administrative and financial relations makes it ver y clear that under the"
"Indian federal system the Centre has been assigned a very predominant role. The States are heavily dependent upon the Union Government. The Constitution has some conspicuous unitary featur es. These are; _ (a) a single Constitution both for the Centre and the States, w ith the exception o f Jammu and Kashmir; (b) a major part of the Constitution can be amended by the parliament alone and the exclusive right of the Parliament to propose amendments; (c) provision for a single all-India citizenship w ith the exception o f Jammu and Kashmir; (d) the power o f the Parliament to change the name, territory or boundary o f States without their consent; (e) the appointment of the governor of a State by the President and his functioning as the agent of the Centre; (f)  a united judiciary both for the Centre and the States w ith the Supr eme Courts  at 1he apex; (g) the representation of the States in the Rajya Sabha is based on population of a State. Thus there is unequal representation to the State in the Rajya Sabha;(h)"
the presence of all-India Services whose appointment is made by the Center; (i) the power of the Centre to impose President rule on States and promulgation of national and f inancial emergenc ies; (j) the right o f the Parliament to
legislate on subjects in State List under certain circumstances; and (k) single election machinery to conduct
elections to the Parliament and State Legislatures.
For this reason some critics have called India a centralized f ederation. It appears that the Constitution makers
"envisaged a ""co-operative federal ism·in which the Union ends the States should collaborate w ith each other for the common good."
