Financial relations
The Constitution provides for a f inancially strong centre so much so the States are almost totally dependent on the
Union. The outstanding featur e o f Indian f inances is that most of the resources accrue to the Union and out of these some are trans ferred to   States.
Scheme of distribution of reven ue
Art.  268 provides the scheme o f the distribution of revenue between the Union and the States . The States possess
"exclusive j urisdiction over taxes enumerated in the State List. The Union is entitled to the proceeds of the taxes in the Union List. The Concurrent List included no taxes. However, while the proceeds of taxes within the State List are entirely retained by the States, proceeds of some of the ta xes in the Union List be allotted, wholly or partially, to the States. The Constitution mentions four categor ies of Union taxes, which are wholly or partially assigned to the"
States:
(i)      Duties Levied by the Union but Collected and Appropriated by the States. Accord ing to Ar t. 268 stamp duties
and duties of excise on medicinal and toiled preparations mentioned in the Union List are levied by the Central Government. These duties are collected by the states within which such duties are leviable. The proceeds of such duties are assigned to the States.
