Legislative relations
"The Constitution divides legislative authority between the Union and the States in three lists- the Union List, the"
"State List and the Concurrent List. The distribution is remarkably elaborate and detailed. The Union List consists of 99 items. It demonstrates the vast extent as well as the great importance of the powers vested in the Union government. The Union Parliament has exclusive authority to frame laws on subjects enumerated in the list. These include foreign af fairs, de fence, armed forces, communications, posts and telegr aphs, foreign trade, inter -state trade, commerce, etc. A number of items included in the list have an impor tant bearing on UnionState relations and some o f them can enable the Union to expand its area of oper ation and ther eby extend its control over the sphere, which falls under State juri sdiction. For example item number 52, which refers to industry, places a powerful lever in"
the hands of the Union to take any industry under its own control.
"Both the Parliament and the State Legislatures can make laws on subjec ts given in the concurr ent List, but the"
"centre has a prior and superior claim to legislate on concurr ent subjec ts. The list comprises of 52 items including criminal and civil procedur e, marriage and divorce, economic and special planning, trade union, labour welfare, electricity, newspapers, books and printing presses, population control and family planning etc."
The state List consisting of 61 items contains subjects on which ordinarily the States along can make laws . These
"include public order, police, administration of justi ce, prisons, loca l government, agr iculture etc. However, what makes State autonomy less real than it appear s at f irst is the fact that under certa in conditions the Constitution authorizes the Union Government to extend its  over matters formal ly included in the State List. In fact, when a proclamation or emergency is in oper ation, Parliament can legislate on matters enumerated in all the three lists."
